Finding Aid for the Baxter, Nathaniel/Robert Jackson Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Baxter, Nathaniel/Robert Jackson Papers
1875-1969
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0036
.42 linear feet
Biography/History
The families of Nathaniel Baxter and Robert Jackson were prominent Nashville, Tennessee families, and closely affiliated with Vanderbilt University. Three generations of the family served on the Vanderbilt University Board of Trust.
Nathaniel Baxter, Sr. [1812-1895] came to Nashville when it was still wilderness. He was an attorney, prominent in the business, legal and social life of Nashville.
Nathaniel Baxter, Jr. [1844-1913] born in Columbia, Tennessee, later became a Senator from Davidson County, Nashville, Tennessee. He joined the Confederate Army at the age of 16. He fought in many battles including the battle of Franklin, was twice wounded during the Civil War, and when discharged had attained the rank of captain. He became a lawyer, businessman, and became Speaker of the Senate in 1911, and a member of the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University.
Jere Baxter [ -1904]. Illiteracy was to his mind the most threatening peril of the times. He was largely instrumental, as a member of the Senate in 1903, in securing the legislation of that session for the improvement of the common schools. He was founder of the Tennessee Central Railroad.
Robert F. Jackson [ -1933], born in Jackson, Tennessee and a 1881 Vanderbilt University graduate, was a prominent attorney and leader in social, civic, religious and educational circles in Nashville. He worked with the following organizations: Nashville Bar and Library Association, Council of the American Bar Association, State Bar Association, Board of Stewards of the West End Methodist Church, Round Table Club, Old Oak Club, and Belle Meade Country Club. He was also a member of the Vanderbilt University Board of Trust.
Mrs. Robert F. Jackson (Mannie B.) [ -1959], a native of Nashville, was a social and civic leader. She worked with the following organizations: West End Methodist Church, Nashville Chapter of the American Red cross, Bundles For Britain, National Society of the Colonial Dames of America in Tennessee, Ladies Hermitage Association, Polk Memorial Association, Garden Club of Nashville, McDowell Music Club, Centennial Club, Belle Meade Country Club, English Speaking Union, and Review Club. For many years, she served as president of the Vanderbilt Aid Society, and the Vanderbilt Garden Club.
The Nathaniel Baxter/Robert Jackson Papers were donated to Vanderbilt University by Mrs. Eunice Holderness Ridley, the grand-daughter of Mrs. Robert R. Jackson in 1976.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear feet collection contains 51 items of which 20 are photographs relating to the lives of the two families, their city, and the university within that city. The collection is divided into four series:
Series I - Nathaniel Baxter and Robert Jackson families
Speeches delivered at the funeral of Jere Baxter, copy of a Tennessee Senate memorial resolution in honor of Senator Nathaniel Baxter, Jr. pamphlets featuring articles on and by Nathaniel Baxter Jackson, and an obituary of Mrs. Robert F. Jackson (Mannie B. Jackson) who originally assembled the collection.
Series II – Offprints/articles - history of Nashville, Tennessee
Historical articles about Nashville, and early medical education in Nashville.
Series III – Programs - Vanderbilt University – History and Events
Programs for banquets, special events, commencement exercises held at Vanderbilt University. It also contains the Court’s decision relative to the lawsuit between the Methodist Church and Vanderbilt, a World War I Honor Roll, and a 1929 survey of technical education in the South.
Series IV - Family photographs.
Baxter, Holderness, and Jackson families.
- Series I - Family Materials – (9)
  - Christmas Card – from Mrs. Robert Fenner Jackson
  - Correspondence – Incoming
    - Pertaining to letters of introduction for Mrs. Robert Jackson (Mannie B. Jackson) to the American Diplomatic and Consular Officers for travel abroad.
      - May 28, 1936
      - May 29, 1936
      - February 18, 1938
  - Addresses, March 1, 1904
    - Dr. J. R. Winchester and Jno. A. Pitts
    - at the funeral services of Hon. Jere Baxter
  - Memorial Resolution
    - Senator Nathaniel Baxter, Jr., October 14, 1913
    - Joint Convention of the Senate and House of Representatives of Tennessee
  - Obituary
    - Mrs. Robert Fenner Jackson, Sr. (Mannie B. Jackson)
    - Nashville Banner, April 7, 1959
  - Pamphlets
    - Commercial Club Tattler
    - Vol. VI, No. 1, April 1917
    - “Old Bullion” 125 Years on Broadway, 1824-1949
    - by N. Baxter Jackson
- Series II – Offprints/Articles - History - Nashville, Tennessee – (5)
  - Nashville’s Dark Decade – The Sixties
    - by Alfred Leland Crabb, The Peabody Reflector and Alumni News
  - The Seventies - Nashville’s Decade of Rebuilding
    - by Alfred Leland Crabb, The Peabody Reflector and Alumni News
  - The Eighties – Nashville’s Decade of Social Assimilation
    - by Alfred Leland Crabb, The Peabody Reflector and Alumni News
  - Early History of Medical Education in Nashville
    - by Owen H. Wilson and Amos Christie
    - reprinted from Journal of the Tennessee Medical Association
    - Vol. 62, No. 9, September 1969
  - Reminiscences on Contagious Diseases and Their Management Before The Acceptance of the “Germ Theory”
    - by Owen H. Wilson and Amos Christie reprinted from Southern Medical Bulletin, Bulletin of the Southern Medical Association, Vol. 57, No. 4, December 1969
- Series III – Programs - Vanderbilt University – History and Events – (17)
  - Dedication of Vanderbilt University, October 3, 1875
  - Commencement, June 15, 1909
  - Commencement, June 16-21, 1911 (2)
  - Court Case
    - No. 27177 R.D. In the Chancery Court of Davidson County – Methodist Church vs. Vanderbilt University
  - Court Decision
    - Opinion of the Supreme Court of Tennessee in the Vanderbilt University Case, Rendered March 21, 1914
  - Football Banquet, November 29, 1909
  - Honor Roll, circa 1920
  - Semi-Centennial Exercises, October 15-18, 1925
  - Celebrating the Fortieth Year of Services of
    - James Hampton Kirkland, June 12, 1933
  - Inauguration - Oliver C. Carmichael, February 3-5, 1938 – (4)
    - Invitation to Reception honoring Chancellor Oliver C. Carmichael and Mrs. Carmichael February 4, 1938
    - Invitation to the Inauguration of Oliver C. Carmichael Feburary 5, 1938
    - Symposium on Higher Education in the South February 3-5, 1938
  - Memorial Services – James Hampton Kirkland, October 27, 1939
  - Conference on Postwar Problems; Business, Education, Government, March 1-3, 1944
  - Inauguration - Bennett Harvie Branscomb, February 4, 1947
  - Report
    - Serving Southern Industry in Vanderbilt University - Technical Education Keeps Pace with the Advancing South, 1929
- Series IV – Photographs – Baxter/Jackson Family – (20)
  - Baxter, Edmund – 3
  - Baxter, Nathaniel, Jr. – 3
  - Baxter, Nathaniel, Sr. – 2
  - Baxter, Jere – 2
  - Baxter, Mary Louise Jones – 2
  - Holderness, Marvin E. – 3
  - Jackson, Robert F. – 4
  - Jackson, Robert F., Mrs. (Mannie B.) – 1